(Singing) I see the moon. The moon sees me.
(تغني) أرى القمر، ويراني.
The moon sees somebody that I don't see.
يرى القمر شخصًا لا أراه.
God bless the moon, and God bless me.
ليبارك الله القمر، وليباركني.
And God bless the somebody that I don't see.
وليبارك ذلك الشخص الذي لا أراه.
If I get to heaven, before you do,
إذا وصلت للجنّة قبل أن تفعل،
I'll make a hole and pull you through.
سأحفر حفرة وأجذبك من خلالها.
And I'll write your name on every star,
وسأكتب اسمك على كل نجمة،
and that way the world
وبتلك الطريقة فإن العالم
won't seem so far.
لن يبدو بعيدًا جدًا.
The astronaut will not be at work today.
لن يكون رائد الفضاء في عمله اليوم.
He has called in sick.
لقد أبلغهم أنه مريض.
He has turned off his cell phone, his laptop, his pager, his alarm clock.
أغلق هاتفه وحاسوبه وجهاز الإشعار والمنبّه.
There is a fat yellow cat asleep on his couch,
هناك قطّة صفراء سمينة نائمة على أريكته،
raindrops against the window
حبّات مطر تتساقط على النافذة،
and not even the hint of coffee in the kitchen air.
ولا أثر لرائحة القهوة في هواء المطبخ.
Everybody is in a tizzy.
الجميع متوتّر.
The engineers on the 15th floor have stopped working on their particle machine.
أوقف المهندسون في الطابق الـ15 العمل على مصادم الجسيمات.
The anti-gravity room is leaking,
غرفة انعدام الجاذبية بها تسريب،
and even the freckled kid with glasses,
وحتى الصبي ذو النّمش والنظارات
whose only job is to take out the trash, is nervous,
والذي يقتصر عمله علي إخراج القمامة متوتّر،
fumbles the bag, spills a banana peel and a paper cup.
يُوقع الكيس ويُسقط قشرة موز وكوب ورقي.
Nobody notices.
لا أحد يلاحظ.
They are too busy recalculating what this all mean for lost time.
فالجميع مشغول بإعادة حساب الوقت المُهدر،
How many galaxies are we losing per second?
كم مجرة يفقدونها في الثانية،
How long before next rocket can be launched?
ما الوقت اللازم قبل إطلاق صاروخ آخر.
Somewhere an electron flies off its energy cloud.
في مكان ما، يتحرر إلكترون من مجال طاقته.
A black hole has erupted.
يتشكّل فجأة ثقبٌ أسود.
A mother finishes setting the table for dinner.
تنتهي أم من إعداد مائدة العشاء.
A Law &amp; Order marathon is starting.
تبدأ حلقة من مسلسل "قانون ونظام".
The astronaut is asleep.
ولا يزال رائد الفضاء نائمًا.
He has forgotten to turn off his watch,
نسي أن يوقف ساعة يده
which ticks, like a metal pulse against his wrist.
التي تدق كنبض معدني على معصمه.
He does not hear it.
لا يسمعه.
He dreams of coral reefs and plankton.
يحلم بشعاب مرجانية وطحالب.
His fingers find the pillowcase's sailing masts.
يمدّ أصابعه لتصل إلى صاري وسادته.
He turns on his side, opens his eyes at once.
يستدير على جانبه، ويفتح عينيه فجأة.
He thinks that scuba divers must have the most wonderful job in the world.
وهو متيقن أن الغواصين يمتلكون أروع وظيفة في العالم.
So much water to glide through!
الكثير من الماء لينسابوا خلاله.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا.
When I was little, I could not understand the concept
في صغري، لم أستطع استيعاب فكرة
that you could only live one life.
أن بوسعك أن تحظي بحياة واحدة فقط.
I don't mean this metaphorically.
ولا أقصد هذا مجازًا.
I mean, I literally thought that I was going to get to do
بل أقصد أنني اعتقدت حرفيًا أن بإمكاني أن أفعل
everything there was to do
كل الأشياء التي يمكن فعلها،
and be everything there was to be.
وأن أكون كل الأشياء التي يمكن أن أكونها.
It was only a matter of time.
لكنها مسالة وقت لا أكثر.
And there was no limitation based on age or gender
ولا وجود لأي عقبات ترتبط بالعمر أو الجنس
or race or even appropriate time period.
أو العرق أو حتى الفترة الزمنية المناسبة.
I was sure that I was going to actually experience
كنت على يقين أنني فعلًا سأجرب
what it felt like to be a leader of the civil rights movement
ما يبدو عليه أن أكون زعيمة لحركة الحقوق المدنية
or a ten-year old boy living on a farm during the dust bowl
أو صبياً في العاشرة يعيش في مزرعة خلال فترة "قصعة الغبار"
or an emperor of the Tang dynasty in China.
أو امبراطورًا من سلالة "تانج" في الصين.
My mom says that when people asked me
تقول أمي أنني عندما كان يسألني الناس
what I wanted to be when I grew up, my typical response was:
عما أريد أن أكون عندما أكبُر، كان جوابي المعتاد:
princess-ballerina-astronaut.
أميرة - راقصة بالية - رائدة فضاء.
And what she doesn't understand is that I wasn't trying to invent
ولكن ما لم تدركه أمي أنني لم أكن أحاول اختراع
some combined super profession.
مهنة خارقة مركبة.
I was listing things I thought I was gonna get to be:
بل كنت أعدّد الأشياء التي ظننت أنني سأكونها:
a princess and a ballerina and an astronaut.
أميرة وراقصة بالية ورائدة فضاء.
and I'm pretty sure the list probably went on from there.
وأنا متأكدة أن القائمة كانت أطول من ذلك.
I usually just got cut off.
ولكن كانت تتم مقاطعتي عادةً.
It was never a question of if I was gonna get to do something
لم يكن السؤال عما إذا كنت سأفعل شيئًا
so much of a question of when.
بقدر ما كان سؤالًا عن متي سأفعله.
And I was sure that if I was going to do everything,
وكنت متأكدة أنني إذا أردت فعل كل شيء،
that it probably meant I had to move pretty quickly,
فسيتوجّب على الانطلاق بسرعة،
And since I grew up in New York City, as far as I could tell,
وحيث أنني ترعرعت في نيويورك، فعلي حد علمي،
rushing was pretty normal.
التعجّل شيء طبيعي جدًا.
But, as I grew up, I had this sinking realization,
لكن مع تقدّمي في العمر، انتابني هاجس مقلق
that I wasn't gonna get to live any more than one life.
بأنني لن أحظى بأكثر من حياة واحدة.
I only knew what it felt like to be a teenage girl
أنا لم أدرك سوى الشعور بكوني فتاة مراهقة
in New York City,
من نيويورك،
not a teenage boy in New Zealand,
وليس صبيًا مراهقًا من نيوزيلاندا،
not a prom queen in Kansas.
وليس ملكة لحفل تخرّج في مدينة كانساس.
I only got to see through my lens.
لم أتمكن سوى من الرؤية عبر عيني فقط.
And it was around this time that I became obsessed with stories,
وفي هذا الوقت تقريبًا، بدأ هوسي بالقصص؛
because it was through stories that I was able to see
لأنني تمكّنت من خلال القصص أن أرى
through someone else's lens, however briefly or imperfectly.
عبر عين شخص آخر، حتى لو كانت قصصًا مختصرة أو ناقصة.
And I started craving hearing other people's experiences
وأصبحت أتلهّف لسماع تجارب الآخرين؛
because I was so jealous that there were entire lives
لأنني شعرت بالغيرة من وجود حيوات كاملة
that I was never gonna get to live,
لن أعيشها أبدًا.
and I wanted to hear about everything that I was missing.
وأردت أن أعرف كل ما يفوتني.
And by transitive property,
وبالتبادل،
I realized that some people were never gonna get to experience
أدركت أن بعض الأشخاص لن يعرفوا أبدًا
what it felt like to be a teenage girl in New York city.
ما شعور أن تكوني فتاة مراهقة في نيويورك.
Which meant that they weren't gonna know
وهذا يعني أنهم لن يعرفوا
what the subway ride after your first kiss feels like,
كيف بدت رحلتك عبر المترو بعد قبلتك الأولي،
or how quiet it gets when its snows.
أو إلى أي مدي يصبح الجو هادئًا بعد تساقط الثلوج.
And I wanted them to know, I wanted to tell them.
وقد أردتهم أن يعرفوا ذلك، أردت أن أخبرهم.
And this became the focus of my obsession.
وقد أصبح هذا مركز هوسي.
I busied myself telling stories and sharing stories and collecting them.
انشغلت بسرد القصص ومشاركتها وتجميعها.
And it's not until recently
ولم أدرك سوى مؤخرًا
In April for National Poetry Month, there's this challenge
في أبريل " الشهر الوطني للشعر"، هناك تحدّي
that many poets in the poetry community participate in,
يشارك فيه العديد من الشعراء،
and its called the 30/30 Challenge.
ويسمى تحدي 30/30.
The idea is you write a new poem
وتتلخّص فكرته في كتابة قصيدة جديدة
every single day for the entire month of April.
كل يوم، طوال شهر أبريل.
And last year, I tried it for the first time
العام الماضي، شاركت فيه لأول مرة
and was thrilled by the efficiency at which I was able to produce poetry.
وقد أبهرتني الكفاءة التي وصلت إليها في إنتاج الشعر.
But at the end of the month, I looked back at these 30 poems I had written
لكن في نهاية الشهر، تفحّصت القصائد الثلاثين التي كتبتها
and discovered that they were all trying to tell the same story,
واكتشفت أن جميعها يحاول سرد القصة ذاتها،
it had just taken me 30 tries to figure out the way that it wanted to be told.
ولكنني استغرقت 30 محاولة لاكتشاف أفضل طريقة لسردها
And I realized that this is probably true of other stories on an even larger scale.
وأدركت أن هذا ينطبق غالبًا على قصصي الأخرى وحتى على نطاق أوسع.
I have stories that I have tried to tell for years,
لدي قصص حاولت لأعوام أن أقصّها،
rewriting and rewriting and constantly searching for the right words.
أعيد صياغتها مرارًا وتكرارًا، وأبحث باستمرار عن الكلمات المناسبة.
There's a French poet and essayist by the name of Paul Valéry
هناك شاعر وكاتب فرنسي يسمي "بول فاليري"
who said a poem is never finished, it is only abandoned.
يقول "لا تنتهي القصيدة أبدًا، بل تُترك".
And this terrifies me
وهذا يُفزعني؛
because it implies that I could keep re-editing and rewriting forever
لأنه يعني أنني قد استمر في التعديل وإعادة الصياغة للأبد
and its up to me to decide when a poem is finished
وأن الأمر عائد إليّ لأقرّر متي تنتهي القصيدة
and when I can walk away from it.
ومتي يمكنني أن أتركها.
And this goes directly against my very obsessive nature
وهذا يتعارض مباشرةً مع هوسي
to try to find the right answer and the perfect words and the right form.
بالبحث عن الإجابة الدقيقة، والكلمات المثالية، والصياغة المناسبة.
And I use poetry in my life,
وأنا استخدم الشعر في حياتي
as a way to help me navigate and work through things.
كوسيلة لمساعدتي على الاستكشاف وفهم الأشياء.
But just because I end the poem, doesn't mean that I've solved
ولكن ليس معني أنني أنهيت قصيدة أنني قد حللت
what it was I was puzzling through.
ما كان يحيرني.
I like to revisit old poetry
أحب أن أعود لشِعري القديم؛
because it shows me exactly where I was at that moment
لأنه يوضّح لي أين كنت بالضبط في تلك الفترة
and what it was I was trying to navigate
وما الذي كنتُ أحاول استكشافه
and the words that I chose to help me.
والكلمات التي اخترتها لمساعدتي.
Now, I have a story
الآن، لدي قصة
that I've been stumbling over for years and years
ظللت أتعثّر فيها لسنوات وسنوات
and I'm not sure if I've found the perfect form,
ولست متأكدة إذا ما كنت قد وجدت الصياغة المثالية،
or whether this is just one attempt
أم أن هذه مجّرد محاولة
and I will try to rewrite it later in search of a better way to tell it.
وسأحاول إعادة صياغتها لاحقاً كي أبحث عن طريقة أفضل لسردها.
But I do know that later, when I look back
لكنني أعرف أنني عندما أنظر للوراء لاحقًا
I will be able to know that this is where I was at this moment
فإنني سأتمكّن من معرفة أنني كنت هنا في هذه اللحظة،
and this is what I was trying to navigate,
وهذا ما كنت أحاول استكشافه،
with these words, here, in this room, with you.
باستخدام هذه الكلمات، هنا، في هذه الغرفة، معكم.
So --
لذا --
Smile.
ابتسم.
It didn't always work this way.
لم يكن الأمر بهذه السهولة دائمًا.
There's a time you had to get your hands dirty.
هناك وقت حيث كان لابد ليديك أن تتسخا.
When you were in the dark, for most of it, fumbling was a given.
عندما تكون في الظلام، ففي أغلب الأحيان يكون التعثر مؤكدًا.
If you needed more contrast, more saturation,
إذا أردت المزيد من التباين، والمزيد من التشبّع،
darker darks and brighter brights,
ظلالًا أدكن، وإضاءةً أسطع،
they called it extended development.
يطلقون على ذلك عملية الإظهار.
It meant you spent longer inhaling chemicals, longer up to your wrist.
مما يعني أنك استنشقت الكثير من الكيماويات، امتدت حتى معصمك.
It wasn't always easy.
لم يكن الأمر بهذه السهولة دائمًا.
Grandpa Stewart was a Navy photographer.
كان جدي ستيوارت مصورًا في البحريّة.
Young, red-faced with his sleeves rolled up,
شابًا، أحمر الوجه، مشمّر الكمّين.
fists of fingers like fat rolls of coins,
قبضتين من أصابع ضخمة كأعمدة من العملات،
he looked like Popeye the sailor man come to life.
بدا كنسخة حيّة من باباي البحّار.
Crooked smile, tuft of chest hair,
ابتسامة معقوفة، شعر صدر كثيف،
he showed up to World War II, with a smirk and a hobby.
جاء للحرب العالمية الثانية بابتسامة متكلفة وهواية.
When they asked him if he knew much about photography,
عندما سألوه إن كان يتقن التصوير،
he lied, learned to read Europe like a map,
كذب، تعلّم أن يقرأ أوروبا كخريطة،
upside down, from the height of a fighter plane,
مقلوبًا رأسًا على عقب، من ارتفاع طائرة مقاتلة،
camera snapping, eyelids flapping
مع لقطات كاميرا وجفون ترمش،
the darkest darks and brightest brights.
الظلال الداكنة والإضاءة الساطعة.
He learned war like he could read his way home.
عرف الحرب مثلما يعرف طريق منزله.
When other men returned, they would put their weapons out to rest,
عندما عاد الآخرون نحّوا أسلحتهم جانبًا
Opened a shop, turned it into a family affair.
فتح متجرًا وجعله مشروعًا عائليًا.
My father was born into this world of black and white.
وُلد أبي في هذا العالم المطلي بالأبيض والأسود.
His basketball hands learned the tiny clicks and slides
تعلّمت يداه الكبيرتان الأماكن والحركات الدقيقة
of lens into frame, film into camera,
لتثبيت العدسة في إطارها، والفيلم في الكاميرا،
chemical into plastic bin.
والكيماويات في وعائها.
His father knew the equipment but not the art.
عرف والده الأدوات، لكنه لم يعرف الفن.
He knew the darks but not the brights.
عرف الظلال، وليس الإضاءة.
My father learned the magic, spent his time following light.
تعلّم والدي سحر التصوير، وأمضي وقته في تتبّع الضوء.
Once he traveled across the country to follow a forest fire,
ذات مرة، سافر عبر البلاد ليتتبّع حريقًا في الغابة،
hunted it with his camera for a week.
لاحقه بالكاميرا لمدة أسبوع.
"Follow the light," he said.
كان يقول "تتّبع الضوء".
"Follow the light."
"تّتبع الضوء."
There are parts of me I only recognize from photographs.
هناك أجزاء مني لا أدركها إلا من خلال الصوَر.
The loft on Wooster Street with the creaky hallways,
الدور العلوي بشارع "ووستر" الذي تصدر ممراته صريرًا،
the twelve-foot ceilings, white walls and cold floors.
أسقف على ارتفاع 12 قدمًا، حوائط بيضاء وأرضيات باردة.
This was my mother's home, before she was mother.
كان هذا منزل أمي، قبل أن تصبح أمًا.
Before she was wife, she was artist.
قبل أن تصبح زوجة، كانت فنانة.
And the only two rooms in the house,
والغرفتان الوحيدتان في المنزل
with walls that reached all the way up to the ceiling,
التي امتدّت حوائطهما حتى السقف،
and doors that opened and closed,
ولهما أبواب تفتح وتغلق،
were the bathroom and the darkroom.
كانتا الحمّام، وغرفة التحميض.
The darkroom she built herself,
غرفة التحميض التي بنتها بنفسها،
with custom-made stainless steel sinks, an 8x10 bed enlarger
بأحواض من الصلب المقاوم للصدأ مصنّعة حسب الطلب ومكبّر 10x8
that moved up and down by a giant hand crank,
يتحرك لأعلى ولأسفل بيد تدوير ضخمة،
a bank of color-balanced lights,
وصف من أضواء موازنة الألوان،
a white glass wall for viewing prints,
وحائط زجاجي أبيض لعرض النُّسخ،
a drying rack that moved in and out from the wall.
ورف تجفيف يتحرك داخل الحائط وخارجه.
My mother built herself a darkroom.
بنت أمي لنفسها غرفة معتمة.
Made it her home.
جعلت منه بيتها.
Fell in love with a man with basketball hands,
وقعت في حب رجل كبير اليدين،
with the way he looked at light.
وطريقة نظره إلى الضوء.
They got married. Had a baby.
تزوّجا وأنجبا طفلة.
Moved to a house near a park.
وانتقلا إلى منزل بجوار حديقة.
But they kept the loft on Wooster Street
وأبقيا الدور العلوي بشارع "ووستر"
for birthday parties and treasure hunts.
لحفلات أعياد الميلاد ولعبة البحث عن الكنز.
The baby tipped the grayscale,
أطاحت الطفلة بدرجات الرمادي،
filled her parents' photo albums with red balloons and yellow icing.
وملأت ألبومات صور والديها ببالونات حمراء ومثلّجات صفراء.
The baby grew into a girl without freckles,
كبرت الطفلة لتصبح فتاة بلا نمش،
with a crooked smile,
ابتسامتها معقوفة،
who didn’t understand why her friends did not have darkrooms in their houses,
لَم تفهم لِم لا توجد غرف تحميض في منازل أصدقائها،
who never saw her parents kiss,
لَم تر والديها قط يتبادلان القبَل،
who never saw them hold hands.
أو يتشابكان الأيدي.
But one day, another baby showed up.
لكن يومًا ما، جاء طفل آخر.
This one with perfect straight hair and bubble gum cheeks.
هذا الطفل كان ناعم الشعر وممتلئ الخدّين.
They named him sweet potato.
أسموه "حبة البطاطا".
When he laughed, he laughed so loudly
عندما كان يضحك كان يضحك بصوت عالٍ
he scared the pigeons on the fire escape
حتي أنه يُفزع الحمَام على سلم الطوارئ.
And the four of them lived in that house near the park.
عاش أربعتهم في هذا المنزل المجاور للحديقة.
The girl with no freckles, the sweet potato boy,
الفتاة التي بلا نمش والطفل "حبة البطاطا"
the basketball father and darkroom mother
والأب كبير اليدين والأم ذات الغرفة المعتمة
and they lit their candles and said their prayers,
وأضاؤوا شموعهم وأدّوا صلاتهم،
and the corners of the photographs curled.
وتجعّدت حواف الصور.
One day, some towers fell.
ذات يوم، انهارت بعض الأبراج.
And the house near the park became a house under ash, so they escaped
وأصبح المنزل المجاور للحديقة منزلًا تحت الرماد؛ لذا هربوا
in backpacks, on bicycles to darkrooms
بحقائب الظهر وعلى درّاجاتهم إلى غرف التحميض،
But the loft of Wooster Street was built for an artist,
لكن الدور العلوي بشارع "ووستر" قد بُني لفنّان،
not a family of pigeons,
وليس لعائلة من الحمام.
and walls that do not reach the ceiling do not hold in the yelling
والحوائط التي لا تمتد حتى السقف لا تحجب الصراخ،
and the man with basketball hands put his weapons out to rest.
والرجل ذو اليدين الكبيرتين قد نحّي أسلحته جانبًا.
He could not fight this war, and no maps pointed home.
لم يستطع خوض هذه الحرب، ولا خرائط ترشده إلى المنزل.
His hands no longer fit his camera,
لم تعد يداه تناسبان الكاميرا،
no longer fit his wife's,
أو تناسبان يدي زوجته،
no longer fit his body.
أو تناسبان جسده.
The sweet potato boy mashed his fists into his mouth
وأَقحم الصبي "حبة البطاطا" قبضته في فمه
until he had nothing more to say.
حتى لم يعد لديه ما يقوله.
So, the girl without freckles went treasure hunting on her own.
لذا ذهبت الفتاة التي بلا نمش للبحث عن الكنز بمفردها.
And on Wooster Street, in a building with the creaky hallways
وفي شارع "ووستر"، في مبني تصدر ممراته صريرًا،
and the loft with the 12-foot ceilings
ودورٍ علوي ارتفاع أسقفه 12 قدمًا،
and the darkroom with too many sinks
والغرفةٍ المعتمة بها الكثير من الأحواض
under the color-balanced lights, she found a note,
تحت أضواء موازنة الألوان، وجدت ملاحظة،
tacked to the wall with a thumb-tack, left over from a time before towers,
معلّقة على الحائط بدبوس، متروكة منذ زمن ما قبل الأبراج،
from the time before babies.
منذ زمن ما قبل الأطفال.
And the note said: "A guy sure loves the girl who works in the darkroom."
مكتوب فيها "رجلٌ يحب بصدق فتاة تعمل في الغرفة المعتمة".
It was a year before my father picked up a camera again.
مرّ عام قبل أن يتمكن أبي من استخدام الكاميرا ثانيةً.
His first time out, he followed the Christmas lights,
في أول مرة خرج فيها، تتبّع أضواء عيد الميلاد،
dotting their way through New York City's trees,
وهي ترسم طريقًا منقّطًا بين أشجار نيويورك،
tiny dots of light, blinking out at him from out of the darkest darks.
نقاط صغيرة من الضوء تومض له من عمق أحلك الظلال.
A year later he traveled across the country to follow a forest fire
بعدها بعام، سافر عبر البلاد ليتتبّع حريقًا في الغابة،
stayed for a week hunting it with his camera,
ظل يلاحقه بالكاميرا لمدة أسبوع.
it was ravaging the West Coast
كان الحريق يدمر الساحل الغربي
eating 18-wheeler trucks in its stride.
يلتهم شاحناتٍ ضخمة في طريقة.
On the other side of the country,
وعلى الجانب الآخر من البلاد،
I went to class and wrote a poem in the margins of my notebook.
ذهبتُ إلي صفّي المدرسي وكتبت قصيدةً في هوامش دفتري.
We have both learned the art of capture.
كلانا قد تعلّم فن الالتقاط.
Maybe we are learning the art of embracing.
ربما نحن نتعلّم فن التقبُّل.
the art of letting go.
ربما نتعلّم فن التخلّي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)